Mic is on.
No.
Screen is shared.
Browser.
So uh, just uh before starting and uh.
This morning I had a very nice interview
with the team that is developing.
So the VD8 VD8 is a vector database is
rather known.
I developed the the the library for
accessing it from.net.
Now they're developing the.
The.net support uh internally,
so they asked me to have an interview.
Someone that is speaking so out.
Oh, it's mine. Sorry.
I don't know.
OK, sorry.
And and so we had a very nice discussion
about the design of a library or sensing
a vector database from a programming
language.
And part of the code that I developed in
the virtual version actually will be
copied by them into the into the product.
And we had some nice discussion about the
use of custom attributes to annotate and
decorate the fields so that you can
control it.
The behaviour of the connector with the
database through reflection.
So as you can see things happens all the
day and then the conversation you have
are.
This kind of conversation.
Having said that,
let's go back to our business.
Which I think is here.
Right.
So yesterday we basically started
browsing the.
The code base that we learn that browsing
a large code base is not that easy and
especially is not something that you do
starting from the main notes from the
entry point on some other place.
And the only way to face and really
appreciate a a system is that you must
understand the problem first,
the application domain, because we humans,
we tend to.
Use meaningful names in classes, etc.
So it's always a good idea to.
Study in the domain even before
approaching the the the codebase.
If you can find documentation as we did,
that's surely helpful,
so that's a good thing.
And then you can start digging.
Don't pretend to understand everything.
If you have to change it,
do it carefully because in a code base,
in a big code base there there are a lot
of hidden assumptions.
Becoming big.
So typically you find things.
The other thing is you have to figure out
whether some feature is in there.
So typically you're not learning by
reading, but typically you say OK,
this is a virtual machine,
a virtual machine.
Some properties that we studied and I
know that this thing should be something.
There should be some way to do this.
Let's go around and look for this thing,
not vice versa. Let's go around and find.
Bumping to the thing I was looking for.
I'm happy, OK,
because sometimes things are subtle.
So yesterday I didn't.
Use this because I didn't want to start
today with this this thing.
So you remember the object class and
remember we said OK, there is the.
A method table pointer that points to the
method table and in fact since we have
one method table for every type,
it also identifies the type of the object.
Uh,
but some of you may remember that I
mentioned that you pay.
More than 4 bytes for each object,
but when we read the code,
the object class only possessed 4 bytes,
the pointer or depending it may be even 8
bytes. It depends on the architecture but.
Uh the the the the the pointer size uh to
the to the to the uh class so.
Where the other information that I
already mentioned at some point,
which is the synchronization block is
available. So if we go to the object.
Let me search because I mean we don't
have time to.
This is the common base part to all
sealer objects.
It contains the method table point and
the sink block index,
which is a negative offset. OK,
so in the layout layout they decided to
have.
A memory layout in which a part of every
object is not accessible starting from
the zero,
so from the base point to the object,
but it is defined as negative offset.
OK, um.
Of course you could have.
It's like having a a day starting from
zero or one minute.
It's a convention that it would have
worked with also in the other way around,
but the point is that as you can see.
Since they are basically piggyback on top
of the C++ compiler. Oh yes,
this is another thing that I didn't
mention as much as it should. runtime.
net is written in C++.
As it was from those days.
So this means that the memory layout you
do inherit some runtime support from C++
and you may wonder why we are not using
the same layout of C++ objects. OK.
And the reality is that to the semantics,
as we did with the whitespace compiler,
the semantics of runtime object of C++
may not be equivalent to the semantics
we're going to achieve in in our runtime.
OK, so we we can't rely.
And map things on on the C++ features.
And so basically you have to think that
the programmer that brought this code was
thinking in terms of layout of the memory
to create the abstraction,
not in terms of C++ objects.
And C was OK because it allows you to
control every single bit in the memory
layout so that you can create your data
structures. For instance,
strings are completely different.
net strings or Java strings from C
strings and so.
You need to have a dedicated class which
implements the runtime string,
which is different from the string
provided by your language.
So now the question becomes.
Where do I find this sync block?
Because if you start browsing this thing,
it's not in there. OK,
so I don't wanna spend too much on this.
So I go straight to the solution.
There is a beautiful sync block file
which contains the synchronization block
and also an explanation of its purpose
and why is every object is preceded by an
object header.
So it's not just the same block,
it's there is a an header of the object
and it is other negative offset.
And the reason,
the real reason is that the header of the
object is an internal representation.
With private fields,
they shouldn't be used.
Right.
I mean the the purpose is I don't want
even to the CLR implement implementers.
I don't want that people to access the
header of the object because these are
internal details for.
Booking keep bookkeeping servicing of the
objects.
It's not part of the specification,
but the runtime will need this
information in this specific
implementation.
You have the implementation,
you may get some different fields and
therefore look at seems like.
The idea to say OK object is a meta table
plus something because meta table is
something that is mandatory and is even
mentioned in the specification.
By the way.
net is a standard has been standardized.
Through ECMA and later to ISO.
So there are you can have multiple
implementation of the virtual machine and
and so the idea was the object OBJ header
contains the.
Non-standard part of the object that are
needed for this particular implementation.
OK, that's the reason.
So the C blocker is basically most of it,
so.
If we look for OBJ header, yes, yes, yes,
yes. At some point there should be.
So the OBJ add, as you can see, can be 8,
four or eight bytes. OK.
Because it depends on the architecture
precision, so whether it's 64 or 32 bits,
which means that every object,
even if you create an empty object cost.
Either 8 or 16 bytes because you pay for
the method table pointer and you pay for
the header of the object.
And if you want to represent an integer
32 bits because actually in the runtime
base types are.
They find the in terms of the way they
work.
So in an integer as in Java is 32 bit
integer is not left to the implementation
on the platform. 32 bits.
This means that if you.
If you box, remember the boxing operation.
If you box the the integer then the cost
will be 4 byte plus either 8 or 16 bytes.
So on a 64 bits architecture an integer,
a boxed integer will cost.
Few 20 bytes, that's it.
So there is a specification of document
which is the one that you didn't store.
No,
I mean what you are showing here is
specific.
Yeah, it's the open source implementation.
Open source implementation,
some part is by specification of somebody.
Exactly. Yeah.
So basically the size of the header is
the in the specification you find there
is the fact that you you got them.
Meta table and the header object? No,
because it's a private decision.
So 334 is C# and so 335 is.net.
The runtime, yeah,
basically back in the past since both
Java and.net were closed source,
then Microsoft said OK,
we release the specification on a
standardization body.
Anyone can implement a runtime compatible
with.
With this and in fact Mono as big as big
was implemented and used for several
years and was another implementation of
the runtime and and then.
I think it will be.
I mean if you want to make an exercise,
it's it's interesting to read or I mean
it's a quite big document,
but you will learn a lot of.
Uh,
things by reading the specification of
the of the runtime.
Right. Let's go back to.
Was looking. There we are.
O.
Uh, the synchronization. It's interesting.
Uh.
The uh.
To synchronize,
they use 32 bits anyway and is this
volatile and sync and sync block value OK?
But if you are a 64 bits,
you simply declare another the word.
The words is a 32 bit integer,
so the word.
Which is unused just to align things into
the memory. OK,
so you always have to remember how things
gets laid off, laid out in there.
I mean the compiler uses a lot of
assumptions.
Typically in pretty much all the
languages,
if you write fields in the order,
they will be simply laid out sequentially
into the memory,
but you have to consider some phenomenon,
some architecture.
Align data to 30 degrees.
So in this case you need to insert some
padding to ensure that everything aligns
to get it.
Otherwise it would be too expensive to go
down and unpack the thing OK.
So especially in C++ or C code,
you will see a lot of these three
processor directives that are used to
control these aspects so that the memory
layouts is the most definition possible
given the particular architecture.
And the the layout of the memory,
especially in implementing objects,
is really,
really important because guess what if
you.
Right in the order from the base class
down to the derived class,
the fields of of of an object,
then the operation of outcasting.
It's easy because you simply move the
base point.
Not to point to the part of the with the
pointer pointing to the object,
basically you can see all the fields or
only the fields of the base class.
And so basically just reinterpreting the
memory will give you the.
The inheritance relation.
Notice that this is true only if you have
a single instance inheritance. OK,
so this is true only if I have a.
A sequence of classes that enates one
from the other on a single line with
fields. In that case,
the base pointer is the base pointer to
the class and also to the object on the
the other classes up to the root and
that's easy.
If you want to do multiple inheritance,
this is terrible because this is not true
that the memory layout is the same and so
to access some fields you have to jump in
the in this structure because clearly
there will be the common part and then
the.
Uh,
parse that that they're coming from
different uh inheritance uh relations uh
into into the layout.
And so this is one of the reasons because
uh Java and then.
net and pretty much everyone has said OK,
thanks uh.
OK to multiple,
but we restrict a little bit so that
interface is just a mental table but
without any state and so I can I the
layout of the memory is the easiest one
and the most efficient one.
Perhaps the most the main reason,
because multiple inheritance has been
ditched by many systems at some point,
because it's so much more convenient to
have a single inheritance from the
standpoint of implementation that
everybody.
I buy it to them. OK,
so that's the header and basically an
instance of this class is preceding every
object and as you can see you have some
helpers, but helpers are OK.
They don't occupy space into the memory
plus the state which is a negative offset
with respect to the the thing.
So basically.
We create in the little machine the
object abstraction by just a position of
two objects of C++. OK,
that's curious and we use a point in
between of these two objects into the
memory and that.
OK, right.
Let's go back to.
Uh.
No.
To the documentation and let's have a
look at other interesting parts.
Of uh uh.
Of the book.
Of the runtime.
Um.
So I will spend a little bit of time on
type system because at the end of the day
the contribution of.
net and Java was to have a runtime
support for programming languages.
The rich text system. And again,
you know we need garbage collection to
have a garbage collection.
We need precise memory information.
We learned that.
That is essential,
and so since we need to to have the full
layout of all the objects at runtime,
why don't we create a runtime which other
elements types?
In itself it makes sense because in any
case you will need that information for
implementing the garbage collection and
so in any case that is needed. OK.
So as you can see,
when you start browsing things using your
knowledge of how the system should behave,
it makes sense. I would have started.
I mean I started from damage collection
because.
We spent some time on garbage collection,
so for me it was easier to start from
that page and the market and compaction
and everything.
It's very well similar to what we
described,
but otherwise I would have started with
the types, because types are kings.
I mean that being in Java or in.net,
you have to voice the entry point is a
static method. OK,
so type is king and since the type is
king.
You have the the the main information
about the interesting part.
So major data structure one day and by
the system method table we already bumped.
The EE class.
The EE class EE we already commented.
This stands for execution environment.
EE class is basically the runtime
representation of a.net class.
So loaded into the memory,
so the type loader that is big enough to.
To be worth having a a chapter in this
because that is crucial in these elements.
Basically reads the binary and allocates
EE classes so that in the memory of the
runtime.
The EE class is available there.
Notice that the lifetime,
the lifespan of an EE class is program
execution almost in the sense that.
Uh,
it is such a core notion that the class
can be loaded but can't be unloaded.
Because making the class loadable and
unloadable,
it will be so expensive in terms of
performance that nobody ever thought
about it. In fact, both Java.
Java's notion which is called class
loader that you can customize.
So in Java the class loader is the type
loader which dynamically fetch some
source and creates the equivalent of the
EE class in the Java with virtual machine
memory.
Andin.
net there was the the loader uses a box,
a container which is called the
application domain.
So inside the processor.
net processor you have multiple
application domains.
And in Java you can unload the class
loader in.
net you can unload the application domain.
All the types inside this box will be
unloaded,
but these are traumatic operation that is
really done.
I mean there are use cases,
but I mean it's it's expensive.
The other thing that is true for instance
for.net is that if.
If you call invoke methods of objects of
a different application domain,
so I have an object living in an
application domain.
Another object living in another
application domain and these two
application domain lives inside the same
process.
Even if they are in the same memory,
even if they are generated by the same
just in time compiler,
nevertheless they use interoperability.
So when you invoke the object on the
other application domain,
it's like invoking a method.
Of a different process. OK,
so remember marshalling,
marshalling will be done and marshalling
will be done and you pay a lot of cycles.
This to stress the fact that you need
this big block and big boxes.
Uh and E classes once they uh loaded the.
It's difficult one that without
restarting the program.
Then there is the method desk,
which is clearly description.
It is the descriptor of the method,
the field descriptor,
the type descriptor and the cluster.
OK and guess what?
Method descriptor,
feed descriptor and type descriptor are
the basis for reflection,
our information needed by the run down to
book keep and ensure the execution.
And you know what?
Let's expose them also to application for
implementing the introspection part of
the reflection,
which is I want to look inside me and see
what what's happening. OK.
Type loader.
Use it to load types and create most of
the primary data structure.
10 cast too.
So there are operations in the type
system of.net and Java.
The typical example is the downcast.
OK,
so I have a a reference to an object of a
of a class A and I wanna.
Convert into a reference to an object of
the class B where B met from A.
That is down.
So you're going down in the inheritance.
That check can be performed statically.
And so you need a runtime type check.
It does a little bit of cost at runtime
and the contrast is exactly this report
to this this this thing.
And then obviously.
So this is this gives you an idea of how
the type system is central to the
functioning of a complex from time.
Honestly,
this is also for the Python runtime.
This is also for the JavaScript runtime,
for the Go runtime.
I mean we're starting this because it's
it's richer,
but basically this design is similar.
It's simplified because clearly if the
runtime is a single language.
Without many fields,
then it would be easy to implement,
but basically the constituents are
exactly the same.
OK also Python uses the garbage collector,
it has objects and so.
Similar needs as the Java dotnet runtime.
So this is basically errors.
Errors give you an idea of the type
system. So the the type system.
The loader,
the type system depends from the loader.
The cheat interface just in time depends
on the type system.
Obviously the garbage collection depends
on the type system.
The JIT, the Jct.
compiler depends both the the sorry
depends on the interface of the JIT and
the GC depends on the Jct. compiler.
Uh.
Depending system the the meta depends on
the meta data.
And reflection is the initial part in the
intersection, the generation of code,
security and type system depends one on
each other, basically dependency.
Application domain AD loader type system
depends on application domain and and the
loader.
The reflection depends on the type system,
so as you can see.
Everything is intertwined.
Basically this is the full runtime.
All the services,
the the core services are mentioned in
there.
OK.
O.
Bet me.
There are a few keywords that one I like
and that we will take down uh today.
So first thing that you have to get
familiar with is the name the stub.
Have you heard the name stub in English?
Table is basically something that actor
as a placeholder and.
Will pretend to offer service but it
actually not implementing service that is
stop OK and the virtual stop dispatcher
is a very important element of the
virtual machine and also very clever part
of the implementation.
Because we said that by code,
the base compile machines such as java.
net are resigned so that the by code can
be compiled.
So there are tools that in.
net it is even a part of the design.
There are tools that allows you to
precompile.
The high head of timing compile support.
So basically you read the assembly,
you read all the methods,
you compile the methods so that you
already have the the machine code.
The vector machine keeps working as usual,
but you already have all the.
The code of the methods already compiled,
but it is more common.
The main one typically is program size
that simply runtime module that is called
the JIT.
The just in time compiler is responsible
for compiling methods on demand.
And the.
net implementation implements a clever
trick.
That makes the runtime.
Remember when yesterday I said there are
two implemented.
There is the interpreted light
orchestrator in which the runtime is the
orchestrator.
Say I call this then you get the return
of that and.
It's a on the execution.
Another approach is that I layout things
so that when I say go at some point I'm
sure that it will call me back when
needed.
So I'm generating the things so I can
generate also hook.
That can point to me and I'll be invoked.
The the stab in the meta table is one of
these examples. So the meta table,
when a title is loaded,
is initialized with a pointer to a
section of code that is the same.
For all the application which is the stub,
which basically says that we not get
confined, there's no method here. OK,
but your code does take the method stub.
So the method the table finds the
location of the index of the method you
want in poker.
You jump to the location and you jump to
the stub.
The stub triggers the the just in time
compiler, the just in time compiler.
Given the location of the call that is in
the method table that is in in the in the
in the the bound to the time knows where
they might go this and so.
From the call, just from the call,
he knows how where the bytecode is,
given the bytecode compiles in a
dedicated heap.
So beware also the JIT requires a neap.
Because you need a place where to store
the generated code.
So in the code heap you will get the
binary code at the end of the compilation.
Notice I said that.
Object dot sorter.
So you will expect the sorter and invoke
it. But actually you did.
You didn't do the sorter.
So far you see the invoke the the JIT has
finished so.
As soon the compilation finishes,
there is the second step which is the
back patching.
We already encountered this term.
Same idea in the context of a garbage
collection.
Back patching was if you move the object,
you have to obtain all the references so
that.
The guarantee stays coherent and guess
what? Same thing here.
So once the stub triggers the just in
time compiler,
just in time compiler fails,
compiles the bytecode,
then the method table is backpacked.
And then to the method you get a
different address which is not anymore,
but it is the actor code and then you
jump to the actor code because I see I've
invoked the sort method and then that
method gets invoked. OK, so.
If you understand this basic principle,
it's the the rest of the runtime is
tricky, but it's.
That's easy to understand. OK,
and the good thing is that if I try to
measure the cost in terms of operation of
performing this thing,
the cost is pretty much the same as the C
or C++ 4.
OK,
so you pay me when you hit the first time
the stop, the stop triggers the the, the,
the, the compiler after that invocation.
Then you don't pay any more on the
compiling,
but it is like having the compiling
definition, OK?
Java that had the the just in time
compiler as an add on.
As a different strategy,
there's a similar operation,
but actually the first I don't remember
there was a number something like the 1st
50 application invocation of a method are
interpreted because you are interpreted.
And after you you you cross the number,
I remember it came up a little longer.
Then the G is pretty good under the
principle that if you involve few times a
man,
it's not worth paying the cost of the
computation, OK.
In this respect, the design of.
net and Java is radically different
because.
net has been designed to be compiled and
so there is no or refresh of any
interpreter and everything is basically
up to the services provided by the
runtime.
OK.
This I again,
I suggest you to read this not for.
Don't think about the examiner.
It's an interesting bread for you. OK,
I don't think there are other things.
Yeah, I was remembering.
Something.
OK,
this is the layout in memory of testing.
So there is the meta table. No,
I was looking.
Do another diagram.
No, I mean, there are interesting facts.
Let me tell you this. This is a nice one.
I'm sorry,
there are things that I so this is
interesting.
So the notion of static is ill defined or
it's well defined in the sense of the
semantics of the language, but.
Uh, post some issues.
So now by now you know that any language
typically has static memory. Uh.
Automatic memory. The stack of variables.
Set it up. Dynamic memory. OK,
these are the three years of memory.
In fact the static memory is global and
in a multithreaded application you may
have some synchronization problem because
the different and visibility of the same
static elements.
So uh,
there is the ability in the runtime. Uh.
To annotate, there we are.
There is a custom attribute that what it
is. I see it. OK,
here the address static attribute that
allows you to say this be the static by
the static.
Into the local memory of the not of the
process.
So two different threads executing the
same class.
It will see different values for the
static potentially see different values
for the static members because the
programmer said that I want that this
static.
Everything is static to the current
thread and not to the process. OK,
this is another element that makes a
distinction between Java and net.
Java was more around a bit clean and say
contain.
net was more like I wanna give you the
ability to hook into the runtime.
To be as performer as a safe holder and
so this is clearly something that a
programmer may want to do and so I give
you the ability to do it even if you are
in a safe type safe environment.
OK, I don't think there is much.
Uh, more interesting things.
So.
Let's go to the method descriptor that we
said that is, uh, an important thing.
Let me skip. I was looking for this.
Diagram,
which is another diagram that is really
important important so.
The method descriptor describe the
methods,
so clearly it is related to the method
table.
I have one type type as a method table
that we don't.
Uh, there's lots of. Of course,
the method table may have, uh,
the section of the negative methods.
From the base class or from the interface
and then so the the thing I said about
the layout of the memory field supplies
also to the map table.
The method table is wanted type and it
contains all for every method there is
the slot with the pointer the code.
Of that method and the descriptor as you
can see basically gives the information
about the method,
the number of the slot inside the method
table so that.
The meta table stays as thin as possible.
OK, why?
Because you may remember from your
architecture course,
inside the CPU there are caches.
And cache is very important.
There is one cache,
2 cache and whenever you break the cache
barrier, you have to wait a lot of cycles.
So the size of the runtime.
Data structures are important and so when
they design the all the reflection
related information about the types in
the runtime,
they tend to split the data structures
that are conceptually together.
In two smaller pieces so that there is a
hot part and a cold part.
The hot part is the one like the meta
table. Meta table gets invoked.
It's like being cached. OK,
the meta desk most of the time is not
needed so.
Uh,
even if from a programming standpoint you
may think it will be OK having a a meta
table of method desk and inside the
method desk adding the point that it
would work would have been working.
The same from a performance perspective,
it makes much much more sense to separate
the two data structures so that the hot
part is in cache and the rest will be
accessed only if needed and this.
Tends to improve the performance.
On the whole stuff.
Yeah.
And this is the mechanics I was
mentioning before.
So as you can see there is the method
desk describe the the relates in the slot.
It may it may be linked to the code,
but typically this lot points to the
pre-code which as you can see is I loaded
to the EAX register the pointer to the to
the management filter.
And then you jump to the stop.
So you know that in that register you
have to point that the the stop knows how
to do and then it triggers it triggers
the digest in time and then you backpack
this slot to point straight to the native
coder instead of.
Of the to the.
OK, I don't think that there are.
Yeah, there is a.
Here, as you can see here,
you've also find the.
The.
Uh,
assembly fragments relevant to understand
the internal working of the of the
runtime.
OK.
Now it's time to introduce.
Few other elements that are really
important. The stack.
The stack is king in modern programming.
We already mentioned it.
We said that there are these records that
are called activation records.
Which basically contains.
Function arguments and local variables.
So whenever you call,
which at the end of the day is simply a
jump to a location recorder,
a machine language develop,
you preload on top of the stack.
So whatever thread you have a stack
pointer.
Which traditionally stored in a specific
register of the CPU because the CPU is
aware about this thing and the stack
pointer is the top of the stack.
You simply allocate the new that you
change the top of the stack.
And of course you have to provide enough
information to unwield this stack
allocation.
So you you have to record that in the
stack itself the eight.
Of the of this activation record and the
return address because that is not
statically known.
The return is depends on who is what and
so typically when you call you set the
return address so that.
At the end of the function,
the CPU will jumps back to the return
address and keep run. OK,
so the stack is very, very important.
And the net stack is one of the.
Coolest implementation of stacker I am
aware of.
Beats beauty.
So they use the number of tricks to do
some magic. Why?
Uh.
When?
When you are in C#.
And you invoke a method.
Then you allocate allocate an activation
record which is known as managed.
So managed is a term which refers to the
code that is managed by intermediate OK.
So if I invoke AC sharp method or a sharp
method,
then I will get a managed record on top
of a static.
But suppose that this managed the.
C# function invokes some DLL function of
the operating system.
This function will need some stack space
for its inner work because a stack is
also for the C code,
not just for the networks, so the.
Architects had this brilliant idea to
allow a single stack for all the
invocation, those of the runtime,
but also those of the internal runtime,
because sometimes you call an internal
function.
Each internal function will need a stack
frame.
And so.
The stack become a very complicated
structure which reflects not only the
managed code, but all the invocation.
But clearly this complicates some tasks.
Why? Because it I mean if I called the uh.
An operating system functionality.
This operating system functionality calls
a function. They call the function.
And you know what? I pass the pointer,
the reference to a method of mine.
You know in C you can pass a pointer to
an ADMC, OK,
so that it can be called back by the C
itself.
Uh, so.
Suppose I have a function in C.
This function takes as input a function
pointer.
Internally it calls the function pointer.
So from the managed code C# I invoke this
AC function.
And I pass the reference to a method
which is basically a function.
So I pass it to the unmanaged code,
nothing code, no.net code.
This calls another internal.
It's in the library.
It calls another function, another stack.
This internal function calls the pointer
that I passed from C# and so.
Now there is AC sharp method that gets
invoked from the C code and so another
managed stack frame will be allocated and
so on. So as you can see.
The stack of the magnification is super
rich and you need a lot of machinery in
the runtime to be able to inspect the
stack.
Why stack inspection is important?
On this of course is the thread.
Why stack inspection is important.
The 1st and most important reason is
garbage collection.
We said that most of the roots of the
mark phase of a collector starts from the
cell.
And so the stack and clearly I don't want
to look for roots in the unmanaged.
I don't care about this.
I want to start here and then navigate
the manager.
A stack frame and ignore the remaining
frames.
And the technique they used is brilliant.
They basically annotate the stack with
small data structures that are called
stack frames.
So basically before calling the C code,
you insert few bytes in the stack
annotating.
I just call this OK and so on so that you
can.
Browse this stack with this additional
data structure so that you can be
constructed which part is managed,
which part is not,
which class or method refers to so that I
know for the reference pointer to the
heap and I then recall the stack fully.
At any time, OK.
Add.
Here you got the.
A description of this behavior I just
outlined. And guess what?
You have a full discussion about.
All the frames.
So in the VM there is a frame dotation
header file with all the frames.
And as you can see there are a lot of
frames. Pre stub method frame.
It represents a call to pre stub stub
dispatch frame represent a call into the
virtual call stop manager.
P invoke call iframe protects argument
where the call to together is made and so
on. OK,
so the technique with this is really
ADVANCED technique.
The technique they used is they annotate
the stack.
Of the thread so that at any time the
runtime can go and can go and perform a
step worker to reconstruct fully for many
purposes. For instance, the P invoke.
P invoke stands for.
Platform Invoker, what it was this one.
P Invoker is a feature of the runtime
stands for Platform Invoke.
So the thing that I mentioned yesterday
about the fact that you can annotate the
method and say.
DLL report Monday. OK,
so basically I can say this man,
this is DLL and this is the name of the
endpoint and and you get all the
interface and the marshalling and the of
the arguments made for you.
Generated for you by the runtime itself.
So that is called clustering more.
Clearly if I invoke AC method,
the C method can go around into the map.
In fact you need some.
It's considered an unsafe operation
because.
And actually protects argument when a
call to the get IEL staff or collide is
made to get a create IEL staff for a
manager.
So they tried to introduce enough
information to for instance check whether
the stack is has been corrupted by an
external.
Code or not,
that is the purpose of that particular
frame. OK, so by annotating the stack,
you can.
You can.
There is the debugger because sometimes
you need the debugging and the debugger
you love to be able to stop in the
execution.
Of course the runtime to support the
debugger must introduce some elements,
otherwise you wouldn't be able.
To have a debugger.
Uh, exceptions, of course.
And and so.
Here you find all the the frames.
So this is the frame is a class. Again,
they use the fact that C++ precisely
defines the layout in memory of the C++
classes.
So whenever you see a class in a code
complicated as this,
you don't have to think as a just as a
software engineering entity.
Is a way to have a layout of a memory
with some method attached to to to them.
OK,
so it's more than that and and so you get
some methods and and there is the frame.
Frames type. There is a list.
Frames frame. Oh,
I don't remember where it is.
It's too late.
There are I think it there are the the
there is a there are a dozen frame types
in the in the runtime.
So it's a extensively used this technique
to mark the the stack.
Using these frames.
And then there is an interface which is
super crucial that is called stack Walker,
which is responsible to encapsulate in a
single place the process of stack walking
and then you pass the function to the
stack Walker so that for every frame that
should be inspected.
Given the nature of the stack work,
you would be called back with the
information that has been annotated.
Uh.
And that's uh.
That's an important part.
Type loader.
So.
This is the typical when you create an
instance and you get a type,
the object points to the type,
but in fact it points to the method table.
But we said that there is a one method
table per type, so it is equivalent.
It's just.
Uh.
Oh.
That's interesting. OK. Actually,
I did my internship with Andrew in
Microsoft Research. I didn't know this,
OK.
So uh.
This is.
The setup.
Type uh the the data structure user the
to describe types inside the runtime. Oh,
by the way,
I forgot to say one very important thing
about um.
Type in the in the net which are very
different than Java and many other
languages so typically.
You see,
when you do a complicated runtime,
then you you require skilled people to
maintain and develop it.
If you simplify the design,
you will find more people to work,
able to work.
But actually, um.
You have in the.net type.
They wanted to go beyond the
discrimination of value types and
reference type or typical job in Java in.
Is not inherited from object.
This is clearly rules in the design and
at some point a solution of work has been
let's introduce a wrapper we call integer
which represent an object.
With an integer value. OK,
NET was interested in having a fully
single deep detect system where
everything was inherited from object on
and so.
The decision was let's keep a little bit
of C++.
So in C++ you know that there are types
and and there is the location location.
If I have a class in C+,
if I say new then the object is allocated
into the heap.
If I if I declare a local variable of
that type,
then the value is allocated on the stack.
OK, so in C++ the allocation,
the position of allocation is orthogonal
to the class.
In Java,
all the class types are in the heap,
so no way to allocate on the stack
objects set reference class.
The integers, the numbers,
they are stored on the stack and they are
always copied around. OK,
so at the end of the day,
this makes difference in terms of the
copy. If you copy an object,
you are copying the reference of the
object. If you copy a value,
you have a copy of the.
The bits of that value, that's the one.
So in document they try to have a more
flexible component. So they said OK,
the type system has a very tight.
And reference that if you declare,
I tell you in C# which is easier.
OK if in C# I declare a class that is a
reference.
So if I if I say new of a class.
That will the object will be annotated in
the it's garbage correct.
If you declare a strut.
That is a very and therefore the
semantics of that structured object is
the one of coping bits like integers and
other.
How many type in eggs?
In any case, from object. So the compiler,
whenever you upcast a value type
including an integer into an object which
is the superclass,
automatically the compiler will emit A
boxing instruction for you.
So basically it creates a a a wrapper
with the object header and the the bits
are included and this is allocated into
the heap and it becomes a reference type.
So in the.net world.
A type can be inserted in the object in
the heap,
and if there are two objects without any
need to create any class that browse the
value itself, you may say OK,
this is just for theory, no?
There are easy data structure that are so
inefficient. Now you know why.
I mean if if I am creating a 2D graphics
or a 3D graphics application.
OK,
let's say I use 32 bits to represent the
coordinates on a screen. OK, so XM1.
In if if I allocate value types,
I just pay 8 bytes to store the
coordinates of my system.
If I if I want a 64 bit platform which is
normal today and I do the same.
Then these eight bytes become suddenly
painful.
So you understand that for?
Very importantly,
useful data structures such as points,
points, 3D, complex numbers,
and it can go on and on.
The dichotomy of the class types is very
tight in Java is terrible because if you
want to do the right thing in software
engineering, you pay a lot of rent.
A lot of because of all the object had
that that also Java has you have to pay
for.
The meta the meta table pointers you have
to pay for. OK in.net they said no.
So let's allow to create the value types,
structured value types.
In Java you have you have integer impact
if you look at the American
implementation in Java.
They use the integers X into X into Y.
You use explicitly to arguments instead
of having a class and process for
efficiency purposes. That is 1 technique.
There are others techniques to do the
same, but basically.
Is always is rooted to this.
So you see that understanding the
internals of the runtimes allows you to
make a wide decision in your
implementation hopefully.
And so.
The the types are are loaded. Oh.
Um, let me stay on this schema now.
Because I didn't spend enough time to
this schema.
net as another big difference in Java.
JVM is does not support the parametric
polygon.
So types inside the Java Virtual Machines
are without parameters.
dot net this a different choice.
Which is not because they were smarter
and Java people's number is that Java
started with I without.
And by the time people started saying,
can we have parameters in types and
methods? It was too late.
There were too many Java Vector machine
installed worldwide to have to replace
all of that. So Java said, OK,
let's find a less impactful
implementation of Java.
.
net was was released in 2001 and in 2004
they released their net itself.
The platform was so young it was
completely acceptable to to do the
extension. OK. In fact,
in Java there was an alternative
implementation made by Robert Cartwright.
That was proposed to some ICC statement,
but eventually they decided to not to go
that way.
So here you see the real difference.
The real difference is that a type
descriptor.
Is related to function so param type of
descriptor type variable descriptor.
So this is these are the parameters so at
runtime if I have stack of T.
Then the type descriptor will have T as a
parameter. OK,
so all the reflection data reflects type
parameters both at the type level and
also at the method level,
because C# allows also for generic
methods.
You can have the parameter also on the
level of the.
Of course there are also the array type,
these people because arrays are treated
natively and so you have also that and
last but not least.net.
Type system has also another feature
which is known as delegate.
Have you ever heard this?
So a delegator is a very simple thing,
very powerful. It was the first attempt.
It's by now it's even different.
Difficult to explain this display.
Oh, gateway timeout is not nice.
Oh, OK.
Huh.
I'm late.
Um.
Here we are. OK,
can you show me an example?
Of delegate creation and.
Used in C#. So to explain delegates,
perhaps the best and easiest way is to.
To use a an example so.
Hey,
we're so used to Lambda pass a single
function as an argument that that is even
difficult to understand why the same was
revolutionary when they did,
but if we go back in time,
Java was having.
Pure uh.
Inheritance approach.
So basically class and interface,
that's it.
So if I needed to pass a function to
another method,
the only option we were left with was to
implement an interface.
OK, so to pass.
Uh.
As I don't know,
an action to a button in the UI to be
involved in when once the button is
pressed required you to implement some
interface.
The interface is OK interface with the
single method.
I don't know in action argument. OK,
it's OK,
but what is the the limit that the type
has a name if I took two different
interface with the same signature?
Those were two different interfaces
because they have a different name.
In C when you have a a a function pointer
of type in the and in return that is the
name.
I don't have a adding so if I pass any.
Function pointer of a function and takes
it and returns it. OK,
so the inheritance type system allows you
to have some sort of high order function
passing.
But with this limit that is bound to the
you have to create and so there was a lot
of extra code to be written in the
especially in the context of the UI and
the web that were main application user
at the time.
And so.net came up with this idea. OK,
let's introduce the delegate type.
The delegate type is like the type say
version of the function point of C So
this delegate type.
That we call math operation is something
that takes 2 integer and returns one
integer. OK,
so any method that supports that
signature to me is OK.
What?
Uh, now.
In this case I have a static which is OK,
so add is A + B multiply A * B.
So math operation of OP1 is equal add.
So basically add is a method with the
right signature so you can create a
delegate out of it.
Multiply.
You can do the same and then you can
write line and see the difference and
everything works fine.
Um delegate supports also.
Multicast. This is useful, for instance,
for events.
So when you add some of delegates,
in fact you're not adding.
You basically create a list of function
pointers. So if I invoke the compile,
the combined.
All the methods in the in the list will
be invoked.
So there is a for each hidden down there.
OK,
now here we are considering static
methods.
This will work also with the.
Instance. So the delegatedin.
net is not just the function point,
it's a pair.
It's a pair in which you have the this
pointer because an instance matter to be
invoked requires to know the reference to
the instance of the object. OK.
So it's a pair. One is the this pointer.
If the method is starting,
that pointer will be null or and and
sorry the function that the pointer to
the method. OK, so.
This reflects to the this function
pointer. OK, so in.
net you have value types delegates.
Pointers and.
Parametric types.
And so the description used by the type
loader are more complicated. Oh,
now I don't think I want to. Oh,
there is a yeah.
You see the EE class is the cold data.
The meta table is hot data. OK.
And uh, and that's it. Uh, well.
And this is what happens when you have
generics,
which becomes much more complicated,
of course. I mean,
it's not more complicated concept.
It's just trickier.
You have more code to write,
more cases to consider.
And type descriptor are complicated
because.
You don't want to generate a EE class for
every sensation of the time because that
will cost too much.
So there are a lot of optimization that
are possible.
That's really tricky and beyond the scope
of this class.
How much time have been left?
Reasonably an author to.
Have a one final look.
This is a very overview of the threads.
Threads are are interesting objects.
Thread were were made popular by.
Job. Excellent.
Brands were introduced by operating
systems.
In the in the 90s,
but the the habit was to use some
external library to support threading. OK,
so having a representation of the motion
of thread inside the execution
environment that was Java at first.
Threads are an instance of very important
concept in programming.
So you you entered it because they said
very important. That's it's also waiting.
Threads.
So in as in Java we have a class thread.
But that is a trick that has become these
days so popular that we don't even notice
anymore. The thread is not just a class.
Red is the representation of an active
part of the operating system.
The thread class is not.
Do any other pass into the runtime
because it's not just data,
it represents an executable entity that
you use,
you create and which has a behavior that
is different.
So you can instantiate as many strings
and you're just allocating on the.
If you allocate you say new thread and
you you start it,
you have a completely different dynamics
in the executive. OK,
so threads are important because on one
end.
The the threads sometimes have to
interact with the runtime. Why?
There is collection.
You can't let a thread run and you know
right into the memory while you're.
Remaining points around.
So threats in fact are in the in the when
they call them managed threats which are
system threat plus the ability to spend
its execution at certain point.
Because that is required by the damage
collection.
And a data which represents the thread in
terms of an object.
So basically we created a sort of
imposter that represents a runtime pair,
you know with a runtime object which is.
The um, that's right. This is uh uh uh.
True for threads, it is true for Windows,
it is true for files and many other
objects.
And so nowadays it is quite common to
expose elements.
That are not properly just data.
They have some behavior to map styles and
objects, element of the machine,
whether that is a GPU, a CPU,
a thread and some other thing,
everything gets converted.
In a type of system into a type so that
as a programmer you don't have to resort
to external libraries.
So this is a quite popular pattern and I
think that was a good moment to stress
this so.
The thread clearly as supports for the
synchronization and guess what?
The sync block in the object header is
the same for that is used to implement
synchronization in threads.
So you can use any object to synchronize.
And that's the reason because you can
create instances of the object class
because you can use them as a semaphore.
So if you don't need the extra fields,
who cares?
Because an object is also a
synchronization element.
I don't want it to go more in in in
details.
The only thing that I think it's
interesting is the garbage collector
tries to be as respectful as possible of
concurrency.
So it runs with two modalities.
In one modality basically suspends all
the threads.
So there are tricks that allows the
threads to be suspended because the the
managed code is generated by the JIT,
so the JIT can insert a specific
operation to check and stop a thread.
Thread from execution and once all the
threads are suspended then the garbage
collection can operate.
And of course this stops the full runtime
under some conditions.
You can stop only the threads that are
interested by the objects and the
remaining thread can be left executing
without problems.
So and then there are threads.
Special threads.
There is a thread internally that is the
finalizer thread,
which is a thread which is responsible to
finalize the objects and zero the memory.
That's a special thread that is a
background thread that used.
There are the garbage collection threads.
The debugger thread and uh and the thread
pool threads uh are all these are special
threads inside the the uh.
Virtual machine. So I will like to spend.
I'll be 10 minutes late. I'm sorry,
but so that I I finished this section,
so be a little patient.
I want to show you.
So do you agree that the runtime is not?
An easy code base. OK,
so I forked the runtime.
When you fork on GitHub,
basically you create a new copy of the
rebel, OK.
Now I have a.
net runtime on my GitHub and Codex,
which has been launched by a few months
ago. Unfortunately,
it's not free available,
but it makes sense. As you will see,
it costs a lot of resources,
so it makes sense that you have to pay.
The allows you to attach them.
You can also use the use the open source
version which is cool.
You can find it on Github.
It's called CLI.
Recommendation and execute it inside at
least a container. OK,
because some genius lab run and BI which
execute the common line commands on the
laptop and get down into the database
files, etcetera.
Because the in case of allocination,
it can go very bad. Uh, so uh.
This is correct.
So I basically attach it to my repo to a
particular branch main of my vehicle the
thing.
And now I can ask question and also ask
to do bug piece or code changes.
That AI will perform.
So what I'm gonna do now is to.
Ask uh.
A question about so how?
Uh.
Oh.
Um.
Hmm.
Let me first start so.
Um, does the GC uh?
Stops all the threads.
To operate.
OK, so that's my question to the AI.
So now this is an agent. OK,
what does it mean by the fact that this
is an agent? This is a background task.
It may run for minutes. In fact,
if I look at what's going on.
Actually a container gets allocated in
the cloud.
The system perform a pool of the of the
repo of course since I have an
environment the the.
The the container has been already
populated,
but nevertheless the system will do a
pull in case it does change it and after
this if we are lucky.
And I I can get enough GPU in a
reasonable amount of time.
You will see the AI that will start
browsing the code by using SAD.
SAD is a very old.
Tool from the 70s. It's a Linux tool,
so basically the AI and all the
algorithms that orchestrate the problems.
I use it to analyze the code base.
Not just by having everything in the
context of the model,
but perhaps they use the read, analyze,
read again.
So basically the loop is let's read on
the file.
Find the read me and understand,
summarize, remix, etc. There we are.
Actually you can even configure runtimes
and actually you can even run.
Unique test so that you can check that
proposed changes are sound and.
OK, oh,
probably my previous container has been
ditched,
so it's rebuilding the container from
scratch.
In a short time it will be possible to
create your own container for for these
days.
Uh, and so.
Some pointer. Yeah,
actually that's the default image.
That's the default image of the which
supports Go, Swift and Rust.
So if you ever ask code it's already
there,
you can inject your share comments and
install any other things and then I hope
it will.
Otherwise I have a copy so I already need
this kind of experiment so.
I can reset,
but it's pretty impressive to see it at
work and it's impressive.
No installation were erformed.
LS OK,
so as you can see now the eye is acting,
so it's not just using information in the
model,
but actually it's issuing comments to the
shell.
Reading the out of the common deciding
the next section and then keeps going
until she's reasonably convinced that
producing the right answer.
And what is impressive that in minutes
you will get incredible answers from.
These things which is able to make a
sense of a very large and complicated
codebase giving you both the details.
So where there are the lines of code
which answer to your question.
But also an overview so you can pose of.
Uh.
In Workstation,
I said it here without conclusion,
the connector suspend all managed thread
calling suspend EE before it runs through
the collection phases and only resumes
when restart E after the work is complete.
That is the classic stop the work poster
where no managed threads can execute.
What she runs and of course you have
where this information is coming from and
actually he found she found information
in the book of the runtime and so clearly
she used information.
And when concurrent background GC is
enabled,
so we learned that the runtime can use
the GC in both modes,
which is the default for the workstation
garbage collector.
The runtime still performs shortstop the
worst suspension.
To start and finish the background
collection.
But most of the marking as weeping
happens on the background garbage
collector thread while other managed
threads keep allocating and executing.
So basically they have two implementation,
one is thread safe and is able to.
In background,
but of course you have to briefly suspend
everything before starting the macro base
because you have to say oh you have I'm
doing the collection where and so the the
the the managed code will change
behaviour to cooperate with the garbage
collector until it would be a problem.
And also this has been extracted.
So I can also ask for can you show me
where the right barrier of the GC?
Gets updated when a reference is set.
OK,
now should be much quicker because the
container is already allocated,
as you said,
but by doing that we're not actually
learning how to do it.
That's correct. That's correct. In fact,
I mean not entirely because in the second
part of the course we will start to do
some practice on how we use AI
programming here.
And and it's not entirely correct.
Basically if you say write me this if you
write OK,
then you have to review the pull request
anyway.
But in this way you can get a comment of
the full code and.
In the AI,
the most important part is the if you
pose a stupid question,
we get a stupid answer and and so that's
the reason because as part of the
assignment we will expect you to attach
the question you pose to the system and I
will double check the output because
actually.
That is the important part.
Then here as you can I I hope,
but I'm pretty sure so now MD 64 the
helper that executes when the jit meets
and it checks variance.
You see there is write barrier dot S is
an assembly file so they have some
assembly and here I I got the code.
So actually this kind of implementation
honestly is for software.
The block and then this would not be the
last time we'll see this content stuff
because this is going in production right
now in a lot of conference.
So the developer is can you implement the
and the end you get do you want me to
create a new request for this?
We'll go to the You look at it, yes.
I worked with some quite big open source
and the hard part is actually the fine
stuff and if you do it by that you do not
learn how to find stuff. I want to be.
I mean you gave like like my grandpa.
I mean I agree my grandpa said that if we
use calculator we will have lost the
ability to make computations mathematical
calculation by hand, which is partly true.
So clearly it is different.
I mean it's clearly valuable because it
allows to jumpstart work at a speed at
which would be impossible otherwise.
But if you look at the question I just
posed.
I mean that's not a question that tell me
what this thing is about. I said OK,
I know that there is a right barrier.
I know.
Please can you help me find a relevant
place in the culture? OK.
So again it's it's not a tool is how you
used to to get the value. So no,
I don't think that if you're.
A a non a reasonable programmer.
Basically,
it's basically useless to do these things.
If you are a reasonable programmer,
you can pose the right questions, but you.
Should be an advanced program to be able
to read the answer. Yes, exactly.
As you said,
you you made a very because you know what
the GCEs and where you can find to be
partially already know the answer and you
already know about the finding.
That's the one we. Oh, yeah. Oh,
I mean that.
I can say,
can you give me an overview of the
security?
Issues uh in uh coding.
And you can get a full security view on
the runtime.
I don't know what will come out of all of
these and how long will take something
that I'm not going to keep you.
But nevertheless, yes, I agree,
but that's the way it it works.
I mean from the AI,
it's not just the the code that you type
in or you paste it in GPT or.
Uh, others said to get the answer. Uh.
Now this the system.
This is true for this Uh.
Large comp IT company in Giza,
so not in New York or in California.
Is is using a code generator from traffic.
Which is a similar support.
So it is what it is,
but the reality is that the word is
already on that page and clearly it's an
unfair battle if you pretend that OK,
so as you can see.
We we got algorithmic complexity attacks
on collection.
Untrusted keys can be the level
deliberately trigger hash collision or
worst case bucket behaviour in dictionary
and so on really that that that those are
not that big.
They are, but I mean not.
Compiler, Azure, etcetera, etcetera.
I mean that's that's an example and
perhaps it's not complete.
But nevertheless I I thought it was will
be interesting to show you.
Where from the programming standpoint the
I is is not just copilot inside Visual
Studio code that helps you write the
single line code.
Currently we are able to get debugger.
In our city impact at the University of
Pisa,
this week we are accepting the request to
to the record and a production record.
The reality is that we even developed.
1.
An application from scratch using this.
I mean that we said OK,
I need an application which implementsin.
net, a sound through authentication.
These are the keys and I got the record
in five minutes.
And I got a pull request and then I kept
updating the pull request.
So that is becoming common in common.
But my point in showing you this,
it was exactly the one you were saying.
I mean to be productive,
to be useful this thing.
Is the question that makes the difference.
So definitely because you have to become
a good programmer that understands
semantics,
syntax and all the things because to pose
the question that.
You need them to read the answer even
more,
because if you misinterpret the code
generated,
you may accept a line of code that
immediately produce no results.
And then when your car is riding,
you turn left and the car goes right
because someone.
Accept the wrong pull request. OK,
so that's important because the
productivity that this tool brings
inevitably will lead the world in making
the AI generate programs because at the
end of the day it's so quicker,
it's so more effective that that's the
reality.
But at the same time,
without knowing all the things,
you've seen how many things there are
inside at runtime.
Without a full on scanning,
you will basically be unabled and you
will you be you will be controlled by AI
and not vice versa. And that's a risk.
Which is not a risk only for your job,
but also for the humanity,
because then eventually this software
goes into the piece we use all things and
so that that is a problem so.
Thank you.
I think we can stop and have a nice
weekend.